<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached upon the fast-day, June the 18th, 1690 by a presbyter of the Church of England, that swore in the sincerity of his heart, with a full satisfied conscience, to King William and Queen Mary.</title>
            <author>Presbyter of the Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59279</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2643</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19775</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12172886</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12172886</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55476</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59279)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55476)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 877:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached upon the fast-day, June the 18th, 1690 by a presbyter of the Church of England, that swore in the sincerity of his heart, with a full satisfied conscience, to King William and Queen Mary.</title>
                  <author>Presbyter of the Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Lawrence ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. 32.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>William --  III, --  King of England, 1650-1702.</term>
               <term>Mary --  II, --  Queen of England, 1662-1694.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms LXII, 1-4 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55476:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55476:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached upon The Faſt-Day, June the 18th. 1690.</p>
            <p>By a Presbyter of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that Swore in the Sincerity of his Heart, with a full ſatisfied Conſcience, to King <hi>WILLIAM</hi> and Queen <hi>MARY.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>Licenſed <hi>July</hi> 15th. 1690.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Lawrence,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi> 1690.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:55476:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:55476:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALM LXII. Ver. 1, 2, 3, 4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Truly my ſoul waiteth upon God: from him cometh my ſalvation.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> He onely is my rock and my ſalvation: he is my defence; I ſhall not be greatly moved.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3.</hi> How long will ye imagine miſchief againſt a man? ye ſhall be ſlain all of you: as a bowing wall ſhall ye be, and as a tottering fence.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4.</hi> They onely conſult to caſt him down from his excellency, they delight in lies: they bleſs with their mouth, but they curſe inwardly. <hi>Selah.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Book of <hi>Pſalms</hi> is for divers weighty Reaſons juſtly Sacred among Chriſtians, for it contains all the natural neceſſary Doctrines of Holy Religion, it abounds with Pious Ejaculations proper for a Heavenly Mind in all conditions to offer up to God Almighty; and I doubt not but with ſome Church-men, is one of the firſt amongſt the <hi>Hagiographa,</hi> ſince it's well-compos'd Anthems were duly us'd in the ſignificant, and decent, and glorious Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the <hi>Judaic</hi> Ceremonial Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; indeed it is a Common-Prayer-Book, which a man would not wiſh to be alter'd (at leaſt not, if exactly tranſlated) like as the Author
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55476:3"/>of the better part of it was a Princely Perſon, than whom the twelve Tribes could not have elected a fitter to ſit on the Throne of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and Reign over the Lord's Inheritance: But how violent and reſtleſs was the Oppoſition of the Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> in favour of <hi>Iſhboſheth?</hi> They deſpis'd the Holy Oyl pour'd by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd Prophet on the Royal Head of <hi>David;</hi> they rebell'd againſt the ſo openly declar'd Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, and for two years made good their Rebellion, till the pretending Prince, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Son of an abdicated Monarch, impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently provok'd his haughty General to a Fatal Revolt, which brought the body of the Nation to due conformity, for when the main Suppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Faction failed, the malepert under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dealers in traiterous diſobedience, preſently hearkened to Reaſon, plainly diſcern'd their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Duty, and wiſely conſulted their valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Intereſt, as well as any of the more forward Elders of the Houſe of <hi>Judah.</hi> It's probable that after this ſome few unquiet wretches met in cloſe Cabals, laid ſecret Plots, purſued wicked Devices, ſtruggled with weak Forces to dethrone the new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choſe King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> but <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s new-choſe King was the reverſe Image of his Predeceſſor <hi>Saul,</hi> was as careful of the Rights and Priviledges of his Liege People, as he formerly had been of the ſafety of his harmleſs Flocks; was as ready
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55476:3"/>to ſerve the King of Kings, as his Subjects could be to obey him in the due exerciſe of his Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Power: this ſecur'd his new-gain'd Kingdom, this ſet him free from the fear of being thrown down, headlong from the lofty Pinacle of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Honour, to which he was rais'd by the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial grace and favour of God, who inſpir'd him with a Spirit of Wiſdom, and Courage, and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty, which qualified him for that Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing height, and diſpos'd the hearts of the People to love, honour, and obey him: it's probable the murmuring Malecontents might ſometimes promiſe themſelves ſtrange Succeſs in attempting to overthrow his Righteous Settlement; it's more than probable they hugg'd themſelves, when their Treacherous Malice dealing under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand with a Foreign Enemy, now and then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs'd his Affairs, and taught his thoughtful Heart mournful Song, a ſlow-breath'd Tune of heavy Accents; but his <hi>Alexipharmacon,</hi> his Soveraign Remedy was always at hand, which was this— <hi>Truly my ſoul waiteth upon God, from him cometh my ſalvation, he is my defence, I ſhall not be greatly moved:</hi> then follows his Complaint, <hi>How long will ye imagine miſchief againſt a man? ye ſhall be ſlain all of you; as a bowing wall ſhall ye he, and a tottering fence. They only conſult to thruſt him down from his excellency, they delight in lies, they bleſs with their mouth, but they curſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55476:4"/>inwardly,</hi> — plainly to declare the ſenſe of this place, uſefully to apply that part of the Hiſtory of <hi>David</hi>'s Life, to which they refer, is my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent purpoſe: Upon the two firſt Verſes, we need not be beholding to the Critical Remarques of Interpreters, whoſe Learning may ſtand us in ſome ſtead in the Expoſition of the latter — <hi>How long will ye imagine miſchief againſt a man?</hi> The <hi>Greek</hi> word here is an ἅπαξ λεγόμενον ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant only in this place, but meets with compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive large conſtruction, Ye put upon a man, ruſh upon him, deviſe miſchief, ſorrow againſt him; againſt a man— a Poetical expreſſion, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of himſelf in the third Perſon, as if he had ſaid, againſt me, <hi>David,</hi> a ſingle, honeſt, and innocent man: Or, againſt me, <hi>David,</hi> who have ſhewn my ſelf a man, a Champion againſt the Enemies of my King that was, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,— <hi>ye ſhall be ſlain all of you,</hi> — thus Paſſively rendred; this is a Prediction, or Imprecation, which had its event, as is to be ſeen in the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of <hi>Kings,</hi> and the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi>'s ſundry Songs of Deliverance, — <hi>as a bowing wall ſhall ye be, and a tottering fence,</hi> which is eaſily thrown down, and utterly ruin'd. Others tranſlate Actively, Ye do kill, or labour to ſlay me, like a ruinous Wall or Fence, you hang over me, threatning my utter ruine.— <hi>They only conſult to thruſt him down from his excellency,</hi> i. e. me from
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55476:4"/>my Highneſs, from my Royal Dignity, ſo the <hi>Dutch</hi> Annotators, nay, and Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphraſes, to pull me from the Throne, to wreſt the Regal Power out of my hand. Since Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks of ſo different a temper ſuppoſe <hi>David,</hi> when he penn'd this <hi>Pſalm,</hi> a crowned Head, I hope I may proceed on that Suppoſition.</p>
            <p>The Verſion, which by being in our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer-Book, is become Infallible, has this expreſſion — <hi>Whom God will exalt:</hi> With refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to which I ſhall conſider how God exalted <hi>David,</hi> and whether God did not ſo act, as to leave it to the People to have ſome ſhare in it; <hi>They delight in lies, they bleſs with their mouth, but they curſe inwardly,</hi> i. e. with ſubtle and crafty Devices, Lies, and Calumnies, they ſeek to over-reach and ruine me, all and every of them, with their mouth congratulate me, wiſh me well, religiouſly own my Title, and in open Court ſwear Allegiance to me, but their hearts wander after the abdicated Houſe of <hi>Saul;</hi> ſo that all their Humble Addreſſes are but cheating Formalities of Court-Flattery, and their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd Loyalty, a Canting term to palliate a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Treaſon. The Words and Phraſes of the Text being thus briefly explain'd, I will make no nice diviſion of the ſame, by which too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the ſenſe of God's Holy Word is crucified, and the patience of a Pious Auditory abus'd;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55476:5"/>but among ſeveral weighty things, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of which they invite, I ſhall ſelect three as the moſt weighty, and confine my thoughts to them, and they are ſo worthy your attention, that if there were no defect in your Orator, you would liſten with mighty expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and be fill'd in anſwerable meaſure with pleaſing ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>The firſt is, the exaltation of <hi>David</hi> to the Throne of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond, the deſperate wickedneſs of the Enemies of the King, their contrivances to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne him, and their palliating their black De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns with fair words.</p>
            <p>The third, <hi>David</hi>'s aſſurance that he ſhould not be greatly moved, but his Throne ſecur'd, and their rebellious Attempts puniſh'd.</p>
            <p>I will firſt offer my thoughts concerning the exaltation of <hi>David</hi> to the Throne of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and 'tis neceſſary to begin with determining the Right of this; for if <hi>David</hi> did not aſcend the Throne by Lawful means, then he unjuſtly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of the endeavours of the party of <hi>Iſhbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth</hi> to dethrone him: And ſuppoſing the means Lawful, yet the nature of thoſe Lawful means muſt be underſtood, elſe we ſhall not be able to judge concerning their Fact who oppos'd his Authority. Tho' I think none will queſtion but that <hi>David</hi> aſcended the Throne of <hi>Iſrael</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:55476:5"/>by juſt and lawful means, yet it was two years before the generality of the People could be convinc'd of it. The Solemn Ceremony of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Unction, and the Teſtimony of a Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prophet that pour'd it down his Princely Temples, was not preſently receiv'd as full Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, whom God did deſign for the <hi>Jews</hi> to be their King; which is a Moral Demonſtration to me, that when God indulg'd them a Change of Government, he did not abſolutely over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule their Choice concerning the Perſon that ſhould adminiſter it; but retiring from his own more immediate <hi>Theocraſie,</hi> left the new Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to be conducted by the ordinary Methods in uſe among Men. Was then the Sacred Unction to no end and purpoſe? Yes, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable end and purpoſe, as may be very eaſily apprehended, for it ſatisfied <hi>David</hi> that God's gracious Providence was engag'd to exalt him: Fill'd now with the pleaſing hope, and wrapt with the wondrous expectation of the mighty Bleſſing, his mind naturally roſe to high thoughts, and ſallied forth into bold Enterpriſes befitting a ſtout Warriour, and a glorious Monarch. There was ſomething Divine in the Meſſage which prepar'd <hi>David</hi> for the Regal Office, but that which had the immediate happy effect on the People, inclining them to offer him the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, was his true Piety, and ſucceſsful
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55476:6"/>Vertue, his fervent Zeal for God's Worſhip, and his ſenſible concern for the Nations Safety; they ſaw no man ſo forward in regulating the Services of the Temple, no man his equal in Valour, when an uncircumciſed Monſter defied the Armies of the Living God; this brought off their Affections from the Houſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> and the not well-known Son of the worthy <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than.</hi> Had not ſuch an unparallel'd Rival for Power advanc'd a Claim, it had probably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended on <hi>Iſhboſheth;</hi> but the <hi>Jews,</hi> who knew not the ſecret of the Divine Right of Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſet by, fore-clos'd, excluded the neareſt of Kin, not that they juſtly feared he had, or would endeavour to introduce a Foreign Enemy, and an Idolatrous Religion, but only (as near as we can gueſs) becauſe he was not ſo well qualified to Protect them from their Hoſtile Neighbours, and to Adminiſter Juſtice between man and man.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>David</hi> ſucceeded <hi>Saul;</hi> not the eldeſt of his Loyns, no, nor his Son, but by Marriage of his Daughter. A ſpecial act of Providence open'd the way, and he ever after walked evenly, and made the beſt on't. The <hi>Jews</hi> either had forgot his being anointed, or never knew its meaning; but his Prodigious Victories were freſh in memory, he won Suffrages among the Tribes by ten thouſands, <hi>i. e.</hi> as faſt as he ſlew
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55476:6"/>
               <hi>Philiſtines.</hi> Nor was his Skill in Muſick to be lightly eſteemed, which often introduc'd him into the Preſence, to his Advantage, though not without his Danger. Providence had the greateſt hand in his Exaltation, yet the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's Choice was as free as it was good, and was as good as Heaven and Earth could make it. Change but ſome Names, and here you have the very Account of His Excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty King <hi>William</hi>'s Acceſſion to the Throne of <hi>England,</hi> with all its Dependencies. The wary, invidious, and injurious Jealouſie of contriving States-men obſcured his firſt years, with-held from him the due Honours of his Anceſtors, and from his Country an uſeful Protection. <hi>David</hi> was not heard of, till <hi>Iſrael</hi> wanted a Champion to anſwer the proud Challenge of a big-fighting Lubber: Nor the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> the Subject of Publick Diſcourſe, till his mad Oppoſers had ruined themſelves, and betray'd their Nation. Divine Providence, and not Humane Fore-ſight reſtored him to his Rights, and by him delivered a harraſs'd People from the Luſt of a faithleſs and bloody prevailing Invader.</p>
            <p>The Conſecrating <hi>David</hi> by the Prophet <hi>Samuel</hi> was not a more immediate Call for him to ſignalize himſelf, as became a Candidate for Empire, than the Humble Invitation of our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55476:7"/>Spiritual Guides, as well as Civil Patriots, was to the Prince to haſten to the Redemption of our devoted Lives and Liberties. For why? <hi>Samuel</hi>'s knowledge of the mind of God, by whatever means it was revealed to him, could not be more certain and unqueſtionable, than our Reverend Prelates knowledge of the ſame, gathered from the plaineſt Revelation that ever was made in the Holy Scripture. There they learned that Rulers were conſtituted for the encouragement of good men, and for a terror to bad. There they learned to ſuffer with Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience hard meaſure from the hands of their unbelieving Authoritative Maſters, but not to Sacrifice their Lives to the Luſt of Arbitrary Uſurpation, when Wiſdom and Courage might as well preſerve them. If an Invitation from ſuch Perſons, and thus grounded, was not equal to a Viſion, or a Voice from Heaven, by which Deliverers were raiſed up among the <hi>Jews,</hi> why then the Goſpel is a Cloud, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration under the Law was Sun-ſhine. As <hi>David</hi> was not only by receiving the Sacred Unction made to expect a Crown, but alſo from that time forward ſafely guarded, by a conſtant, ſignal, watchful Providence. So our Illuſtrious Deliverer, after his receiving a well-deliberated, Juſt, and Religious Addreſs from the Flower of our Gentry, and the moſt Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55476:7"/>of the Clergy, was conducted by a ſpecial Providence, which loudly proclaim'd all along, that it was God who had raiſed him up, to reſtore our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to deliver our Bodies from the Tyranny of Men, and our Souls from the Doctrines of Devils. The Wiſdom of God infatuated the Counſels of his moſt Formidable Enemy, tempted that proud Son of Violence to ſlight the Deſign, which could not ſo well have been purſued, till his Forces were diverted; and when the Grand Diſturber of Chriſtendom was ſet down before <hi>Philipsburgh,</hi> the Power of God with aſtoniſhing Wonders ſteer'd the Proteſtant Prince's doubtful Courſe through all the dangers of the Deep: For the Storm which his firſt putting to Sea met with, ſome wretched Worſhippers of Saints and Angels thanked the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> but really and truly God of his free Mercy ſent it, which prevented the Happy Expedition no farther, than what ſerv'd to make the Violaters of our Laws and Liberties more imprudent and ſecure: And when afterwards a favourable brisk Gale had carried the Fleet beyond their Port, a contrary Wind was preſently commiſſioned for a few hours, as if for no
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55476:8"/>other end but ſafely to land our Preſervers. In the time of <hi>Saul,</hi> God was with <hi>David,</hi> and ſtrengthed his Arm, ſo that his Sword made Prodigious Slaughter among the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines.</hi> But in conducting the Prince to the Throne, whereon he is now righteouſly ſeated, Providence ſcattered the Enemy like Chaff before the Wind, and gave him a Victory which pleaſed him better than all he had won with the Sword, <hi>viz.</hi> a Victory without Blood.</p>
            <p>Thus far God was (if I may ſo ſpeak) miraculouſly alone in the Advancement of the Prince toward the height of earthly Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; and when the Eyes of the Oppreſſed Nation were fully open, he left it to them to Chuſe their King, in the room of their unhappy miſled Abdicator, and they were not diſobedient to his Providence.</p>
            <p>To ſpeak the truth of this whole matter briefly, it is manifeſt from what we read in Scripture concerning <hi>David,</hi> and what our Eyes have ſeen, and our Ears have heard relating to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> that both the one and the other of them, were by the wonderful Providence of God called forth from their Private ways of Living, in
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55476:8"/>order to be made Kings, and the free Choice of their ſeveral People made them ſo.</p>
            <p>I come now to ſpeak of the Second thing which I propounded from the Text, as moſt fit to be reflected on, that is, the deſperate Wickedneſs of the Enemies of the King, their Contrivances to Dethrone, and their palliating their black Deſigns with fair Words. And here firſt I'le mention what Evidence we have of the Fact, and then touch ſome Circumſtances which aggravate the Enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it.</p>
            <p>The Royal <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> gives us, ſometimes with mournful Eloquence, being in the day of his Diſtreſs; ſometimes with joyful Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents, being happily eſcap'd from Danger, large and paſſionate Accounts of the bold Attempts, and treacherous Contrivances of his Enemies: <hi>They mark'd his ſteps, thinking evil against him;</hi> i. e. they narrowly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd his conduct of Affairs, ſeeking occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to complain of his Male-adminiſtration. <hi>They wreſted his word, and caſt iniquity upon him;</hi> when no fault could be found, they put falſe colours upon things, and reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him. <hi>They curſed him, they belied him, their teeth became ſpears, and their tongue a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55476:9"/>ſharp ſword;</hi> i. e. they curſed him with ſo bitter Imprecations, they belied him with ſuch abominable falſe Suggeſtions, that the plain ſignification of inartificial Words can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expreſs it, and Metaphorical Language perhaps not ſufficiently help us to gueſs at. They derided him, derided him for his very truſt in the Lord; <hi>they conſulted, they only conſulted;</hi> i. e. they made it their chief aim with Hand and Heart, they endeavoured to caſt him from the Throne, though God had exalted him, and the People had ſubmitted unto him; and they that did this were many, and were ſtrong, too many, and too ſtrong for him; but that, <hi>He that hath God his hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per need not be afraid, though ten thouſands of the ſtrongest of the ſons of men ſet themſelves against him:</hi> though they palliate their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns while they are in contrivance with fair words, and as often as they are diſappointed forſwear their unſucceſsful Villany. Thus much, and more to the ſame purpoſe, is to be read in the Book of <hi>Pſalms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Hiſtorical part of the Old Teſtament has not very many inſtances, nor perhaps fully anſwering every Circumſtance of ſo ſevere an Indictment; but I ſuppoſe that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55476:9"/>was, becauſe the Hiſtorical part is but a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious Extract out of Voluminous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords in the Archives of the <hi>Jews;</hi> and yet in the Royal Chronicle we have an Account of <hi>Abſalom</hi>'s Rebellion, of his inſinuating Arts to ſteal the Affections of the People; his engaging (if I may uſe a <hi>Prolepſis</hi>) the <hi>Jewiſh Matchiavil</hi> to his Rebellion; but <hi>Matchiavil</hi> learned of <hi>Ahithophel,</hi> I therefore diſcharge my Alluſion; <hi>Ahithophel</hi> is Name enough to brand a ſubtil Rebel. We read farther, how <hi>Shimei</hi> let looſe a railing Tongue, and lifted up violent Hands againſt the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed King. And alſo how <hi>Sheba</hi> the Son of <hi>Bichri</hi> had likely to have ſhook the Throne more fatally than <hi>Abſalom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you have an Account of the matter of Fact charg'd againſt <hi>David</hi>'s Enemies, their Fact admits aggravation from ſeveral Topicks — Is this the Man whom God rais'd up for the Uprightneſs of his Heart, when he rejected <hi>Saul</hi> for diſobedience? Is this the Man, whoſe ſurprizing Valour fell'd a tall Monument of Pride down to the ground, before whom the whole Army of <hi>Iſrael</hi> trembled? Is this the Man whoſe Succeſs and Triumphs became the theme of every
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55476:10"/>gladſom, honeſt Heart, when they thought upon the Dangers which they dreaded, and the Deliverance which they did not expect? Is this the Man, whom the People choſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Experience of his Merit, to Adminiſter the Government, which they ſo much ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mir'd, that they preferred it before the <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy</hi> it ſelf; it might perhaps have been better for them, to have remained under God's Prophets a while longer; but when they would not be ſatisfied without a King, they could not have made a better Choice than <hi>David;</hi> yet even againſt <hi>David, David</hi> thus uſeful to his Country, <hi>David</hi> thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of his God, the Flatterers of an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious Son, and the unſeaſonable Abettors of <hi>Saul</hi>'s Houſe aroſe, and palliated, as they could, their vile purpoſes with fair words.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſpoke to the Second Head, I'le proceed, as I have begun, and joyn the Parallel.</p>
            <p>With equal wickedneſs as the rebellious <hi>Jews</hi> againſt <hi>David,</hi> unreaſonable, unruly men, <hi>have conſulted to caſt down from his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency,</hi> that's the word in our Tranſlation, from his Throne, our Juſt and Lawful King, King <hi>William,</hi> whence otherwiſe were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55476:10"/>Impoſitions complain'd of, and the repayment of a Debt exclaim'd againſt, the Loan of which preſerv'd our whole? Whence otherwiſe was his Royal Name cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into uncharitable Parties, when he came to ſave the Nation? Whence elſe proceeded the many Forgeries of their Succeſs, who were ever better at Forging than Fighting? Whence elſe flow'd remembrances to his Health, who forſook when he could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy us, by Men, who had not a good word for him in the day of his Power? Whence elſe have diſputing Tongues with the worſt part of Eccleſiaſtical Skill raiſed a Duſt to hide the fair and full appearance of a plain and neceſſary Duty? Is this the Man, whom glorious Providence in a wonderful manner brought from a Private Retirement, to vindicate Oppreſſed States and Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? In a word, Is this the Man, whom the moſt Honourable, and the moſt Wealthy, the moſt Honeſt, and the moſt Brave, the moſt Learned, and the moſt Pious, invited hither, or approved the Invitation, to ſave from Devaſtation, and from Fire, our Land, our Laws, our Liberties, our Bibles, our Lives—Good God! what deſperate Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55476:11"/>is this, that People obliged equal to their wiſhes, but much beyond their expectation, ſhould entertain an unthankful rebellious thought againſt their ſucceſsful Preſerver and Defender of theſe near Concerns? What Villany is it beyond the reach of words to brand with ſufficient Reproach that unquiet <hi>Ahithophel, Shimei's,</hi> and <hi>Sheba's,</hi> ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, and ſtrive to throw him down whom God by amazing Miracles advanced to Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, who ſucceeded on the Throne over us, both by an Hereditary Right, and an uncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Election? What black and new-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented ſin is this (deſerving Puniſhment, I will not name, ſince his God-like Mercy can remit) that they who have acknowledg'd the Hereditary Right of King <hi>William,</hi> and elected his particular for their King, in the vacancy of the Throne, by the majority of their Repreſentatives, and taken their Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Oath, many of them, to defend him, ſhould defie their Oaths, and give their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience the Lie, in Paſſion for a Tyrannous Bigott, whom they always reſiſted after they had made him King, and never began to love, till they had lent their helping hand to make him none. <hi>David</hi>'s Enemies gave him great
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55476:11"/>and frequent occaſion of Complaint, but no Affliction of his was ſo circumſtanced as that related in the 55 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> where he mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Expoſtulates thus. <hi>It was not an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my that reproached me, then I could have born it; neither was it he that hated me, that did magnifie himſelf againſt me, then I would have hid my ſelf from him: But it was thou, O man, my equal, my guide, and my acquaintance, we took ſweet counſel together, and walked unto the houſe of God in company.</hi> How may a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel-complaint be taken up, by him that is, how much ſoever oppos'd, both in Right and Fact our King? It was not an open Enemy only, not one alone that profeſs'd to hate me, that magnified himſelf againſt me; this would not have ſo much ſurprized me, nor ſo nearly have affected my mind; it was not a <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Idolater, nor a <hi>Gothick</hi> Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, nor ſuch a ſenſeleſs Picture of Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity as <hi>Juverna</hi> draws upon cold Boggs, that conſulted to thruſt me away, whom God hath exalted; but it was thou, of late the Reformation's chief Support and Hope, whoſe labouring, over-loaded, and only not yielding ſtrength I haſtened to relieve, but O my Soul, now while I build up, thou pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55476:12"/>down. <hi>David</hi> concludes with Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Rage, <hi>Let, &amp;c.</hi> our Liege Lord with winning Mercy, be forgiven — may his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy prevail over all his Enemies, over him their hatred never, it never ſhall; for to him and <hi>David</hi> one and the ſame aſſurance remains faſt; <hi>Truly my ſoul waiteth upon God, from him cometh my ſalvation, he is my defence, I ſhall not be greatly moved;</hi> and this is the third and laſt Head to be conſidered. And firſt, with reſpect only to the Royal <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> and then to his Parallel.</p>
            <p>Aſſurance is not always well grounded; nothing is more uſual than to ſee the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent fruſtrated of their pleaſing expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and betray'd into ſudden and ſurprizing Miſery: But <hi>David</hi>'s aſſurance was juſt, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably, and ſafely relied upon; it had for its ſupport, not partial ſelf-love, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrues all things in its own favour; nor proud contempt, which leſſens the real ſtrength of an Enemy till the Battel is joyn'd, and then finds it powerfully increas'd: not unactive ſecurity, which ruines the very Favourites of Providence, notwithſtanding their vaſt Advantages. <hi>David</hi>'s Aſſurance was upheld by theſe two mighty Pillars, the Power and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55476:12"/>the Promiſe of God, the fram of Nature does not ſtand firmer; his Royal Breaſt har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd no partial ſelf-love, for he ſpeaks of himſelf in words of the loweſt Humility, and admires the Divine Goodneſs, <hi>which took him from the Sheep-folds, from following the Ewes great with young, to feed</hi> Iſrael <hi>his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and</hi> Jacob <hi>his Inheritance:</hi> reflecting on the uncertain ſtate of his own Affairs, he fear'd his Enemies, complain'd of their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and their ſtrength, he was not unactive and ſecure; for though he truſted not in his Bow, yet he drew the feather'd Arrow to the head, and bravely laid about him with his Sword, the Sword he won from the Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous <hi>Philiſtine,</hi> and with it lopt off the proud Head of its Maſter, but he piouſly own'd his Salvation to have come from the aſſiſtance of the Lord of Hoſts. How weak ſoever a man is in himſelf, and his Friends, yet he muſt needs be ſafe if God Almighty condeſcend to be his Protector, and to fight his Battels. Unto <hi>David</hi> God often promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his Protection, upon Conditions, which no man more diligently made it his buſineſs to perform than he; well might he therefore upon the examination of his own Heart, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55476:13"/>conſciouſneſs of his Righteouſneſs and truſt in God, reſt ſatisfied, that after all the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile contrivances, and bold efforts of his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, he ſhould not be greatly moved; if troubled, yet not over-power'd; if di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed, yet not ruined; if aſſaulted, yet not dethron'd: Well might he, reflecting on the unjuſt and impious daring of his Adverſaries, conclude, <hi>Surely men of low degree are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and men of high degree are a lie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Righteous King ſits on the <hi>Engliſh</hi> with like aſſurance, as <hi>David</hi> on the Throne of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> beloved of all, even beyond the Lines of the Reformation, though no ſelf-lover; as well acquainted with the Strength and Treachery of one Enemy, as with the Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardize and Treachery of another, a vigilant Obſerver, and an indefatigable Providitator againſt both. But after all his Warlike Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, after all his Powerful Alliances, the bravery of his Worthies, and the Courage of his Army, and the ſteadineſs of his own ſtout Heart and Hand, he places his grand Satisfaction in the Juſtneſs of his Cauſe, and fixes his Truſt and Confidence in the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God Almighty, therefore has he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a Monthly Faſt to be obſerved, as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55476:13"/>his Proclamation informs us, in a moſt So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn and Devout manner for Supplicating Almighty God for the Pardon of our ſins, and for imploring his Bleſſing and Protection in the Preſervation of His Majeſty's Sacred Perſon, and the Proſperity of his Arms in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Naval Forces. What can I advance more on this Argument, than is already ſet before you, in that excellent Form of Prayer which we have this day uſed. St. <hi>Matthew</hi> ſays of our Saviour, <hi>That coming to a certain place in his own Country, he could do no mighty works there, becauſe of the peoples unbelief.</hi> Oh let it not be ſaid of our Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soveraign, that he has Victoriouſly led Armies of ſeveral Nations, and done Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders for the Proteſtant Intereſt abroad, but could not compleat the Settlement of theſe now his three Kingdoms, becauſe of our cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſins here at home, our Heats and Animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, our careleſs way of Living, our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable way of Cenſuring; our Diſputes and Cavils, our Diſcontents and Murmurings, our ſecret Luxury, and our publick Railing, our gainſaying Authority, and worſhipping Names given to Change when they become obſtinate in an Error. Remove from us, O
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55476:14"/>God, theſe and all other our Offences, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we have diſhonoured thee, not duly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured our Soveraigns, King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> troubled the Peace of the State, hindred the Succeſs of our Land and Naval Forces, wronged our Brethren, or abuſed our ſelves, ſo ſhall we have hope in thy Mercy; incline us to be hearty in worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thee, to be careful that our Lives be henceforth reform'd as well as our Profeſſion; ſo though our Enemies rage, yet they ſhall imagine but a vain thing; ſo though they ſet themſelves together againſt us, yet ſhall they not prevail, but we ſhall be ſaved both we and our King.</p>
            <p>I cannot but add a word upon occaſion of the Happy Succeſs of our Forces in <hi>Ireland,</hi> under the Conduct of our Lawful King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam,</hi> whoſe Subjects we are by the juſteſt and wiſeſt Act that ever the Repreſentatives of <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> made.</p>
            <p>Bleſſed be the Lord God of Heaven, who hath heard the Prayers of all the truly Loyal and Honeſt Men in the Kingdom, who hath given them their Hearts deſire, and hath not denied them the requeſt of their Lips, in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55476:14"/>covering their valiant and forward King's Head in the Day of Battel, in protecting his Life, in which their Safety was bound up, (which Life was in eminent danger, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry near being took away, as if to ſhew us how unworthy we are of him, and to affect us with a true ſenſe of the many Deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which Almighty God, the God of Hoſts, by his Warlike Hand worketh for us,) in ſcattering the Troops of that unhappy man's profligate Adherents, who fights now only for a Power to deſtroy us; in blaſting the pernicious Hopes and curſed Prayers of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, unconſtant, unquiet, diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Men, who might have every thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to make them eaſie, could they but be ſo, without the Power to Lord it over the Faith of their Brethren; in fruſtrating a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulouſly-labour'd Bloody, Foreign Invaſion, by ſecret vile Practiſes brought about from the moſt barbarous Tyrant, that ever own'd the Name of Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>May theſe ineffable Mercies of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence, which ſo carefully, and tenderly watcheth over the Kingdom of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as alſo over other Reformed Churches, and Injur'd States, be ever marvellous in our
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55476:15"/>Eyes, ſo marvellous, as to cauſe us, when we cannot comprehend them, to endeavour to expreſs a quick, lively, becoming, and pious ſenſe of them, in all Humble Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Commands of our God in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in all Loyalty to our King, according to the Laws of the Kingdom, in due com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance to thoſe Laws, according to every Capacity wherein they concern us,—by which Laws, (the beſt of Laws I believe) may He, the beſt of Kings undoubtedly, long Reign over us, and let all the People, who fear God, Honour King <hi>William,</hi> and ſay <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:55476:15"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>THE Scandalous neglect of the due Obſervance of the late enjoyn'd Monthly Faſt prompted a Perſon of Honour, and good Affection to our Ancient <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, as it is now happily ſettled under King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> to recommend to the Author of this Sermon, the Penning and Preaching a Diſcourſe ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Solemnity.</p>
            <p>In the late Reign 'twas not an Angry Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch could reſtrain the Clergy from thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Commemorating (as it well became them) the Fifth of <hi>November</hi>'s Deliverance: But a late enjoyn'd Faſt, to beg Pardon of our ſins, that they might not hinder the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py courſe of King <hi>William</hi>'s Victories, by which our Laws and Lives have been reſcued from Violence, and are from Violence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, has been not only not Obſerv'd, but alſo in ſome places, with contemptuous fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs a great deal worſe uſed, than ſhall be mentioned, unleſs the Proof be required, by ſuch as did it without ſhame, and would without ſhame deny it.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:55476:16"/>
            <p>To the Printing this honeſt, tho' mean and plain Diſcourſe, the Author was obſtinately averſe, alledging ſome excuſes, which were allow'd, even by them, that loved him too much, and importuned him dangerouſly; yet at laſt he choſe, unask'd, to Print, being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled by an Accident, which, tho' he does not publiſh, he is willing to declare to any Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that may perchance diſcover his Name, and accuſe him, as a pragmatical, medling Fellow, beyond what his particular Station in the World, might be reaſonably conſtrued to warrant.</p>
            <p>He thinks it reaſonable that every Writer be oblig'd to ſet his Name to what he Prints, that ſo the Publick may have ſatisfaction, if injur'd; but he uſes a liberty commonly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, both becauſe the Book-ſeller promiſes to get the Trifle Licenſed, and alſo, for that, as he does not ſeek to be commended (of which indeed there's no danger) ſo neither is he fond of hard cenſure, which yet he does not much ſuſpect from the Friends of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Settlement, and in point of deſerving, has no need to fear from the <hi>Jacobite</hi>-People, who are certainly the worſt of Chriſtians, and of Philoſophers the moſt abſurd, — of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55476:16"/>Philoſophers the moſt abſurd, for they have, now this long time debauch'd their Reaſon, by giving Credit to falſe News concerning the late King's Northern Forces, Foreign Aids, and <hi>Iriſh</hi> numbers; by believing the <hi>French</hi> King's Irreſiſtibility, Heaven defend them from taking up Infallibility, which the Popes may chance to Iay down, if the Succeſſion goes on in one or two good Choices more. I call them the worſt of Chriſtians, the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable <hi>French</hi> Fleet now in our Seas, evinces it. When we have weather'd the Storm, (which a Providential Wind in greateſt part diverted) and of which, bleſſed be God, there is now no great danger, it is to be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, that the unnatural raiſers of it will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their Senſes, and outwardly at leaſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor their unſucceſsful Villany, or elſe be forc'd to be ſo far Loyal as inability to do great miſchief amounts to. If any man ſhould ſeem to wonder at this piece of Zeal from a Clergy-man againſt the faults of ſome of his Brethren, he bids this Reply be made.</p>
            <p>He has been often in the Company of Men of Quality, great Learning, and fair Eſtates, amongſt whom he has often heard the Clergy cenſur'd, for an unhappy, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55476:17"/>Order, who have been in very great part, in all times Authors of the Troubles and Calamities of the Nation; he thereupon reſolv'd, if ever it fell in his way, to offer one word on behalf of the Settlement, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducive (as far as he is able) to the Security of the ſame, which he is glad that ſome Eminent Clergy-men with better Abilities, do honeſtly frequently endeavour; and he wiſhes that more would do ſo, were it but for this reaſon, <hi>That the Lord's peculiar In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance</hi> (as they call themſelves) <hi>may no longer ſtink in the noſtrils of the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Some Books Printed for <hi>John Lawrence</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey, London.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>INſtitutio Grammaticae ad Juventutis captum ſummo ſtudio &amp; arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio concinnata. In qua artis Ratio, &amp; genuina Notio accuratè diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiritur atque enucleatim enodatur. Per</hi> A. M. <hi>M. A. In Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Map of Man's Miſery: Or, The Poor Man's Pocket-Book. Being a Perpetual Almanack of Spiritual Meditations, or Compleat Directory for one endleſs Week. Containing many uſeful Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Prayers, plainly ſhewing every Chriſtian ſo to walk, that he may pleaſe God. <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Man's whole Duty, and God's wonderful intreaty of him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: Set forth from 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. By <hi>Daniel Burgeſſe,</hi> Miniſter of the Word of Reconcillation. <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Advice to Parents and Children: Being the ſum of ſeveral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, by the ſame Author. <hi>In Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
